Guide to the Joseph Urban Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Joseph Urban Papers,
1893-1998
Urban, Joseph, 1872-1933.
135 linear ft. (ca. 11,530 items in 39 boxes; 86 flat boxes; 147 board-portfolios; 12 map case drawers; 45 boxes of glass plates and acetate negatives; 328 set models)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library,
4079423
Biographical Note
Joseph Urban (1872-1933) studied architecture at the Akademie der bildenden Künst in his native Vienna. He established himself as an architect as well as a book illustrator, exhibit designer, interior decorator and set designer often in collaboration with the painter Heinrich Lefler. Urban and Lefler were co-founders of the Hagenbund, an exhibiting society similar to the Secessionists. In 1912, at the age of 40, Urban emigrated to the United States and became the designer for the Boston Opera Company where he introduced the innovations of the "New Stagecraft" from the european theater. After the Boston Opera Company went bankrupt in 1914, Urban began designing sets in New York. He designed the Ziegfeld Follies as well as all other Ziegfeld productions from 1915 to 1932. In 1917 he began designing for the Metropolitan Opera and continued to do so until his death in 1933. From 1921 to 1925 Urban was also the art director for William Randolph Hearst's Cosmopolitan Studios He had branched out to other artistic endeavors since moving to New York including designing shop windows, roof gardens and interior decoration. From 1921 to 1922, he introduced the works of Viennese artists to the United States through his Wiener Werkstätte shop.
He received his license to practice architecture in the United States in 1926 after which he designed homes, buildings, ballrooms, and theaters in New York and elsewhere. Notable examples of his extant architecture are the Paramount Theater Building and Mar-a-Lago in Palm Beach, Florida and the New School and the Hearst Magazine Building in New york.
Scope and Content
Collection contains watercolor renderings, sketches, technical drawings (ground plans, elevations and details), photographs, glass plate and acetate negatives, scrapbooks, set models and some related papers covering Urban's career in Vienna and New York as an architect, set designer, decorator and illustrator. There is a thorough representation of his New York career including his set designs for Florenz Ziegfeld (1915-1932) and the Metropolitan Opera (1917-1933). The collection also contains information on Urban's work for William Randolph Hearst as art director for Cosmopolitan Studios, his exhibitions including his 1921 Wiener Werkstätte store, and his many architectural projects. Biographical information and research gathered by Richard Cole and Randolph Carter including contributions from his daughter,Gretl Urban, and biographical notes and some letters from his widow, Mary Urban, are also present.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 6 series:
Series 1: Vienna, 1897-1911
Series II: Boston Opera, 1910-1914
Series III: New York
Series IV. Biographical
Series V. Other Donations
Series VI: Set Models
Subjects
Boston Opera Company (1909-1914); Künstlerbund Hagen.; Metropolitan Opera (New York, N.Y.); Hearst, William Randolph, 1863-1951.; Lefler, Heinrich, 1863-1919.; Motion pictures--Setting and scenery.; Opera.; Theater.; Theaters--Stage-setting and scenery.; Architecture.; Musicals.; Interior decoration.; Autographs.; Albums.; Architectural drawings.; Audio cassettes.; Book illustrations.; Cartoons.; Catalogs (exhibition).; Costume design drawings.; Drawings.; Essays.; Glass photonegatives.; Greeting cards.; Interior design drawings.; Interviews.; Memorabilia.; Notes.; Paintings.; Photographs.; Photoprints.; Programs.; Scores.; Set design drawings.; Site plans.; Sketchbooks.; Sketches.; Specifications.; Watercolor drawings.; Workbooks.; Architects.; Artists.; Set designers.; Interior decorators.; Ziegfeld follies.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
1955 M-55 Urban, Mrs. Joseph Gift
09/12/1990 M-90-09-12 Research notes and related materials for a book on Joseph Urban. Cole, Robert Reed Gift
M-92-04-17 Papers Urban, Gretl Gift
05/28/1992 M-92-05-28 7 audio cassettes re. Gretl Urban Cole, Robert Reed Gift
10/09/1992 M-92-10-09 Gold cigarette box Urban, Gretl Gift
11/09/1992 92-11-09 91 letters & mss. of Gretl Urban Cole, Robert Reed Gift
1996 M-1996 Papers Moreno, Manuel Gift
1998 M-1998 16 audio cassettes Carter, Randolph Gift
Gift of Mrs Joseph Urban, 1955.
Gift of Gretl Urban, 1987-1992.
Gift of Randolph Carter, 1988 (audio cassettes).
Gift of Robert Reed Cole, 1990 (research notes) & 1992.
Gift of Manuel Moreno, 1996.
Gift of Randolph Carter, 1998.
- Series 1: Vienna, 1897-1911
  This series contains the records of the architecture and design projects from Urban's career in Vienna. It is arranged chronologically divided into five sections: General files-dated, General files-undated, Illustrations, Exhibits and Unidentified. It contains watercolor drawings, rough drawings, technical drawings, photographs, post cards, clippings, playbooks and exhibit catalogs. Of note are the catalogs from the 1902-1908 Hagenbund exhibits and the photographs of the 1908 Kaiserfest.
  - Subseries I.1: General Files
    - Bicycle tournament, May 26, 1897:
      Urban built a canopy for the tournament festival and made contributions to the program
      - Program & description (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Kaiser Jubilee Bridge, 1898:
      Urban won a competition to design this bridge between the Musikverein and the Künstlerhaus for the celebration of the emperor's 50th year of rule.
      - 3 drawings, watercolor, pencil and ink:
      - --Brucke 1, 29x22 cm., sig. (Box B1, Folder 1)
      - --Brucke 2 & 3, 29x22 cm., sig. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - 2 photographs (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bosnian Pavilion, 1898:
      Also built for the Kaiserfest, the celebration of the emperor's 50th year of rule. See also postcard at Avery Library
      - 4 post cards (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Rathauskeller, 1899:
      With Heinrich Lefler.
      - 4 drawings, watercolor/ink on board:
      - --Large dining room, 25x18 cm. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - --Staircase, 30x20 cm. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - --Die Sage vom Kussdenpfennig (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - --Strauss table, 28x22 cm. (Box B1, Folder 2)
      - 2 pencil sketches of murals (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Lamps (Box A, Folder 1)
      - Clipping, Councilmen's room (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - 48 photographs, various views (Box 1, Folder 5 & 6)
      - 4 photographs, various views (Box A1, Folder 1)
      - 51 prints, various views (Box 1, Folder 7)
        [See also print and 4 photographs at Avery Library]
    - Esterházy Estates, 1899, 1903:
      Count Karl Esterházy saw Urban and Lefler's Lady's Room in the Winter Exhibit of 1897/98 at the Austrian museum and commissioned them to design an addition for his country chateau in St. Abraham in Hungary. In 1903 Urban designed a fountain for another Esterházy estate.
      - 8 drawings, watercolor, pencil and ink:
      - --2. decorative detail, 16x17 cm., sig. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - --II: Fireplace, 25x16 cm. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - --III: Bedroom, 22x23 cm., sig. (Box B1, Folder 3)
      - --IV: Room with daybed, 26x21 cm., sig. (Box B1, Folder 4)
      - --V: Corner of hall, 27x24 cm. (Box B1, Folder 5)
      - --VI: Dining room, 27x24 cm., sig. (Box B1, Folder 6)
      - --VII: Reception room, 28x24 cm., sig. (Box B1, Folder 7)
      - --Bedroom, 16.5x24 cm. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Wall Fountain, magazine print (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Wall Fountain, ink drawing, 42x30 cm. (Box C1, Folder 1)
        [See also photograph of chateau at Avery Library]
    - Memorial Chapel for Empress Elizabeth, 1901:
      Kaiserin-Elizabeth-Kapelle at Baden bei Wien
      - 4 drawings, watercolor, pencil and ink:
      - --Memorial, view from gate, 17x14 cm. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - --Memorial, front elevation, 24x23 cm. (Box B1, Folder 8)
      - --Memorial, view from gate, 25x17 (20x14) cm. (Box B1, Folder 9)
      - --Memorial w/ front walkway, 25x17 (20x14) cm. (Box B1, Folder 10)
    - Wähner House, 1900:
      Theodor Wähner was the Commissioner in charge of the Rathauskeller renovation and the editor of Deutschen Zeitung.
      - 2 photographs of building (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Easter note (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Clock, watercolor on board, 27x14 (20x9) cm. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Goltz House, Alexander, 1902:
      Urban built and furnished an addition to the house of artist and Hagenbund member, Alexander Goltz on Granzinger Street 87.
      - 2 drawings, watercolor, pencil and ink on board, sig.:
      - --Room, corner & plan, 29x21 (24x19) cm. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - --Room, table in foreground, 29x21 (24x20) cm. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Von Wiener House and Office, 1902-1903:
      Baron Ritter von Wiener was Minister of Art, director of the Museum for Culture and Teaching and director of the Museum of Arts and Crafts. Von Wiener was a major patron of Urban and Lefler who provided them with government projects. Baron von Wiener took Urban as a delegate to represent Austria at the 1900 Paris World's Fair.
      - 3 drawings, watercolor and ink on board:
      - --Dining Room elevation, 18x30 cm. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - --Study- floor and elevation, 30x15 cm. (Box C1, Folder 2)
      - --Study corner, 30x15 cm. (Box C1, Folder 2)
      - --North side elevation, 40x40 cm. (Box D1, Folder 1)
      - --Office of the Sectionschef von Stadler, 27x18 cm. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - 5 plans (Box C1, Folder 3)
    - Spiesejaal Hotel Restaurant, 1905:
      Katowice, Poland (formerly, Kattowitz, Prussia)
      - 5 photographs of dining room (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Zwischenspiel, 1905
      Burgtheater comedy in 3 acts by Arthur Schnitzler
      - (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Set sketch (Box B1, Folder 11)
    - Hopfner Restaurant, Paul, 1906
      - 4 drawings, watercolor:
      - --Doorknob detail, (16x11) cm. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - --Mantle detail, 20x28 cm. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - --Entrance elevation, 27x26 cm (Box B1, Folder 12)
      - --Fireplace wall elevation, 26x29 cm. (Box B1, Folder 12)
      - --Wall with mural elevation, 29x48 cm (Box C1, Folder 4)
      - 4 photographs of restaurant (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Hölle Cabaret, 1906:
      With Heinrich Lefler. Cabaret in the cellar of the Theater an der Wien
      - 3 elevations, Theater (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - 4 drawings, watercolor on board:
      - --Elevation, mask wall, 7/30/06, 25x29 cm., sig. (Box B1, Folder 13)
      - --Elevation, devil waltz, 24x29 cm. (Box B1, Folder 13)
      - --Elevation, mask wall, 34x24 cm. (Box B1, Folder 13)
      - --Curtain elevation, 7/30/06, 26x27 cm., sig. (Box B1, Folder 13)
      - Photographs of theater and cabaret (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Program (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Urban Home, Nibelungengasse 8, 1906:
      Donated by Robert Cole in 1995
      - Corner of dining room elevation, 30x20 cm. (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Salon ground plan, 34x23 cm. (Box A1, Folder 2)
      - Children's room wall elevation, 26x35 cm. (Box A1, Folder 2)
    - Landau Villa, Dr. Max, 1906:
      Villa am Semmering, Südbahnstr. 83
      - 5 plans, detail drawing (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - 5 detail drawings (Box C1, Folder 5)
      - 7 photographs of house and model (Box 1, Folder 18)
        [See also drawing of furniture in Avery Library]
    - Redlich Villa, Carl, 1906-1907:
      Country house of the owner of the construction contracting firm Redlich and Berger
      - Sketch of house exterior wall, pencil and ink (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - 4 drawings, watercolor, pencil and ink:
      - 2 elevations, Else Redlich's room, 20.5x28.5 cm. (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - --elevation of chair and divan, 23.5x34 cm. (Box C1, Folder 6)
      - --elevation of hall, 22x44 cm. (Box C1, Folder 6)
      - --Garden lamp detail, 18x29 cm. (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Ground plan, ink, 26x24 cm. (Box C1, Folder 6)
      - Ground plan, watercolor and pencil, 41x29 cm. (Box C1, Folder 6)
      - 2 ground plans, 59x50 cm. (Box 14-9-1, Folder A.1)
      - 5 photographs (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Faust I, II, 1906-07:
      Directed by Paul Schlenther with Josef Kainz at the Burgtheater
      - Playbook, German (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Set notes, 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - 2 drawings, watercolor and pencil:
      - --Prologue, Vienna, 1907, 17x21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - --Gretchen's Room, 15x28 cm. (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - 17 set sketches (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - 3 postcards of actors in costume (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Aschenbrödel (Cinderella), Vienna Hofoper, 1907:
      - 4 technical drawings (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Kaiser Jubilee Festzug, June 12, 1908:
      Celebrating the 60th year of rule of the Emperor Franz Josef.
      - 103 photographs of festival (Box 2, Folder 4 & 5)
      - Wiener Zeitung leaflet, 4 p. (Box B1, Folder 14)
      - Program, 12 p. (Box 2, Folder 5)
        [See also photograph of pavilion at Avery Library]
    - Die Meistersinger von Nürnberg, 1908, Vienna Hofoper:
      - --I: Church, 18x24 (14x20) cm. (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - --I: Church B, 34x22 cm. (Box B1, Folder 15)
      - --II: Street, 18x24 (14x20) cm. (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - --III.1: workshop, 18x24 (14x20) cm. (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - --IV: Meadow, 18x24 (14x20) cm. (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - 2 p. libretto cover (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - 15 set elevations (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - 4 set elevations (Box C1, Folder 7)
        [See also Vienna, 1909-11 and Boston January 23, 1914]
    - Suburbs, 1909:
      - 7 plans (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Tombstones and Chapels, 1909:
      - 5 sketches (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - 18 photographs (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - 19 drawings and sketches (Box B1, Folder 16 & 17)
      - Rough sketch (Box 14-9-1, Folder A3)
    - Die Zauberflöte (The Magic Flute), 1909, Leipzig Opernhaus:
      - Libretto (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - 5 p. notes (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - 12 plans and drawings (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Der Fliegende Holländer, 1909, Vienna Volksoper, and Budapest:
      - Libretto (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Volksoper program, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - 2 plans (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - 4 plans, Budapest (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Tannhäuser, 1909:
      - Libretto (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - 9 set drawings (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Program, Volksoper, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Faust, 1909-11, Gounod, Brunswick:
      - 2 watercolor drawings:
      - --am Brunnen, 19x30 cm. (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - --Street, 20x26 cm. (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Osterspaziergang set sketch (Box 2, Folder 12)
        [See also Vienna (Goethe) 1906-07; Boston 2/26/13; Met 11/17/17 and 11/30/23 ]
    - Quo Vadis?, 1909-11, Budapest, written by J. Nougués:
      - 6 set drawings (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Oberon, 1909-11, Charlottenburg:
      - Ground plan, island (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - 8 set drawings (Box A1, Folder 3)
      - 4 drawings & plans (Box C1, Folder 8)
        [See also Met, 12/18/18]
    - Die Meistersinger von Nürnberg, 1909-11, Budapest:
      - 6 plans (Box 2, Folder 6)
        [See also Vienna 1908 and Boston Opera January 23, 1914]
    - Die Fledermaus, 1909-11, Cologne Opernhaus, written by Johann Strauss:
      - 4 set drawings (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Der Rosenkavalier, 1909-11, Cologne Opernhaus, written by Richard Strauss:
      - Libretto (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - 3 set elevations (Box C1, Folder 9)
      - Article, 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Salome, 1909-11, Stuttgart Hofoper, written by Richard Strauss:
      - Set sketch (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Der Ring Des Nibelungen, 1909-11, Budapest:
      - Essay on Wagner, 17 p. (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Set notes & inventories, 25 p. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Das Rheingold, Budapest, Brunswick:
      - libretto (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - 2 ground plans, Budapest (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Clipping of set (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - 10 plans and sketches (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - 4 plans (Box D1, Folder 2)
    - Die Walküre, Budapest, Mannheim National Theater, 1911:
      - Libretto (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - 5 technical drawings (Box C1, Folder 10)
      - 5 sketches and notes (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - 3 ground plans (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - 2 ground plans, Budapest (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Siegfried:
      - 2 librettos (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Clipping of Act III (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - 4 sketches and plans (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - 2 drawings (Box A1, Folder 4)
      - 2 ground plans (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Tristan und Isolde, 1909-11:
      - 2 librettos (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Footwear, watercolor and ink, 32x26 cm. (Box A1, Folder 5)
      - 5 technical drawings (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Lohengrin, 1909-11, Stuttgart Hofoper:
      - 2 drawings, watercolor:
      - --I: River bank scene, 9x11 (6x10) cm. (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - --Costume drawing, 26x24 cm. (Box B1, Folder 18)
      - 4 set drawings, pencil (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Set drawing, pencil (Box B1, Folder 19)
        [See also Metropolitan Opera February 6, 1921]
    - Zigeunerbaron (Gypsy Baron), 1910:
      By Johan Strauss conducted at the Hofoper by Felix Weingartner.
      - 5 set drawings (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Der Junge Medardus, 1910:
      - 4 set sketches (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Mair House, Dr. Bartl, 1910:
      Dr. Mair was the local doctor for Scheiblingkirchen in lower Austria.
      - Ground plan and rear elevation (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - 4 ground plans (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - 3 photographs of house (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Eisenstein House, Viktor, 1910:
      Gregor-Mendel-Strasse 6. Eisenstein was the Vienna representative for the New York Life Insurance Company.
      - (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - 2 drawings, watercolor, sig.:
      - --Front elevation and ground plan, 29x24 (23x15) cm. (Box B2, Folder 1)
      - --ground plan w/ landscaping, 29x24 (24x17) cm. (Box B2, Folder 1)
    - Benvenuto Cellini, 1911, Hofoper:
      - 3 detail drawings (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Götterdämmerung, 1911, Mannheim Nationaltheater:
      - 5 Roller set & costumes designs (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - 12 set drawings (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - 2 set drawings (Box B2, Folder 2)
    - Lanval, 1911:
      Play by Eduard Stucken, Burgtheater
      - 1 drawing, watercolor:
      - --bedroom w/ ground plan (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Set drawing of bedroom (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - 2 technical drawings (Box 14-9-1, Folder A.2)
    - Gudrun, 1912:
      Opera by Ernst Hardt, Burgtheater
      - 4 set drawings (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Subseries I.2: General Files-Undated
    - Freytag Library and Salon:
      - (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Salon, 2 ladies at piano, 28x24 cm. (Box A1, Folder 6)
  - Subseries I.3: Theater
    - Blaue Vogel (The Blue Bird) by Maurice Maeterlink:
      - 12 set sketches (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Czar und Zimmermann, by Albert Lortzing, comic opera:
      - 3 plans (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Eisenhammer, Der, music by Benito Bersa, book by A. M. Willner:
      - Set sketch (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Erasmus Montanus, Ludwig Holberg, play:
      - 5 sketches and notes (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Förster-Christel (The Girl and the Kaiser), operetta by Bernhard Buchbinder:
      - 4 set sketches (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Frau ohne Schatten, by Richard Strauss:
      - Libretto (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Freischütz, Der, see also Met 1923:
      - 4 ground plans (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Garde Officier:
      - Set sketch (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Graf von Luxemburg (The Count of Luxemburg), Franz Lehar:
      - Set sketch (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Iphigenie auf Tauris, by Christoph Gluck:
      - Libretto (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - 2 set drawings (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Jongleur de Notre Dame, (Der Gaukler unserer lieben frauen), by Massenet:
      - Libretto, German (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - 3 drawings and plans, watercolor:
      - --I: outside abbey (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - --Act II: inside cloister (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - --Act III: Chapel (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Königskinder, by Engelbert Humperdinck:
      - Technical drawing (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Landschaft:
      - 2 landscape drawings (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Love's Labor Lost:
      - Playbook, German (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Lustigen Weiber von Windsor (The Merry Wives of Windsor) Opera by Otto Nikolai:
      - Libretto (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Nozze de Figaro (Marriage of Figaro):
      - Libretto, German (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Pariser Leben, by Jacques Offenbach:
      - 3 set drawings (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Puppenmädel, operetta by Leo Fall, Leo Stein and Alfred Maria Willner:
      - 4 set drawings (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Rienzi, by Richard Wagner:
      - Libretto (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Set notes & sketches, 14 p. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Roméo et Juliette:
      - Set sketch (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Rose vom Liebesgarten, opera by Hans Pfitzner:
      - (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - 2 set sketches (Box B2, Folder 3)
    - Schneemann, Der, Erich Wolfgang Korngold:
      - Set sketch (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Sirene, Die, by Leo Fall, Leo Stein and Alfred Maria Willner:
      - 2 set sketches (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Sister Beatrice and Sumurün:
      - Clipping and 2 postcards (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Tiefland, opera by Eugen d'Albert:
      - Ground plan (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Elevation drawing (Box C1, Folder 11)
    - Die Tote Stadt, Erich Wolfgang Korngold:
      - Libretto (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Verborgte Schloss:
      - Set sketch (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Waffenschmied, Der, comic opera by Albert Lortzing:
      - 3 ground plans (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Wallenstein's Lager, play by Friedrich Schiller:
      - Ground plan (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Xantho, operetta by Jacques Richepin and Xavier Leroux:
      - 2 set sketches (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Zerbrochene Krug (The Broken Jug), comedy by Heinrich von Kleist:
      - 4 sketches and notes (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Zigeunerliebe, (Gypsy Love), music by Franz Lehar, book by A. M. Willner and Robert Bodanzky:
      - 1 set drawing (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Subseries I.4: Illustrations
    - Chronika der drei Schwestern, 1899:
      - --3 illustrations, 23x39 cm. (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - --Medieval street scene, p.8, 24x28 cm. (Box B2, Folder 4)
      - --p. 34, 29x24 (28x23) cm. (Box B2, Folder 5)
      - Bookbinding, 1899, watercolor, 21x30 cm., sig. (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Grimm's Fairy Tales, 1904:
      - --4 illustrations (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - --Der Froschkönig, 24x25 cm. (Box A1, Folder 7)
      - --Rapunzel, 24x21 cm. (Box B2, Folder 6)
      - 8 p. Marienkind, 1905 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Kling Klang Gloria, 1906:
      - --cover, 24x21 cm. (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - --cover, 23x23 cm. (Box A1, Folder 8)
      - Kaiser Calendar, 1898, 24x16 cm. (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - Bookcover, 1910 Unsere Freiland Stauden, 29x20 cm. (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - Andersen Calendar, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Undated:
      - 16 miscellaneous drawings (Box 4, Folder 21)
      - Wienermännergesang verein poster, 48x25 cm. (Box C1, Folder 12)
      - Imperial Border, 40x27 cm. (Box B2, Folder 7)
      - Wilhelm II of Germany tribute, 39x20 cm. (Box B2, Folder 8)
      - 23 borders and ornaments (Box 4, Folder 21)
      - 8 borders and ornaments (Box D1, Folder 3)
  - Subseries I.5: Exhibits
    - Jubiläums-kunst exhibit 1898:
      - catalog (Box B3, Folder 1)
      - 3 photographs of furniture, 1898 (Box 4, Folder 22)
      - Hevesi article, 4 p. (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Hagenbund Exhibition Hall, 1901-1902:
      - 5 drawings, watercolor and pencil, sig.:
      - --Entrance, 37x26 (36x25) cm. (Box B2, Folder 9)
      - --Perspective of Hall, 28x17 cm. (Box 4, Folder 22)
      - --Side elevation, 18x28 cm. (Box 4, Folder 22)